# Harshitha Machiraju











#### **About Me**

I am a **Machine Learning Researcher** focused on enhancing the robustness of neural networks by evaluating and addressing challenges posed by **adversarial** perturbations, **image corruptions**, and **background** variations.

Recently awarded a **PhD** from EPFL under the supervision of Prof. Pascal Frossard and Prof. Michael Herzog, I have developed various methodologies to uncover **biases** and fortify the **robustness** of deep neural networks to **distribution shifts**.

#### **Education**

Sep. 2019 - Apr. 2024 PhD in Machine Learning - EPFL, Switzerland

Advisors: Prof. Pascal Frossard & Prof. Michael Herzog

Jul. 2014 - Aug. 2018

B.Tech in Electrical Eng. - IIT Hyderabad, India

Summa cum Laude & Minor in Comp. Sci

## **Experience**

Sep. 2019 - Apr. 2024 **Doctoral Assistant** at EPFL, Switzerland

Conducted research on enhancing the **robustness** of vision models against diverse **out-of-distribution** inputs, including **image corruptions**,

background and adversarial alterations

Sep. 2018 - Aug. 2019 Research Assistant at IIT Hyderabad, India

Conducted research on designing better adversarial attacks to emulate

realistic weather conditions to assess the robustness of autonomous

navigation systems.

Jul. 2018 - Aug. 2018 Research Intern at UNIST, S. Korea

Conducted research to establish a better relationship between topology

of latent representations and model predictions.

## **Projects**

- Test time Input Processing against Image Corruptions: Proposed EREN, a novel, differentiable image processing algorithm tailored to the spectral biases of models. EREN enhances model robustness against diverse image corruptions and achieves superior performance.
- Automating Out-of-Distribution Sample Generation by Leveraging Model Biases: Proposed MUFIA, an
  innovative algorithm automating the generation of out-of-distribution samples by harnessing model
  spectral biases. This work represents a significant advancement in the field, characterized by its
  utilization of spectral biases for the generation of adversarial image corruptions.
- Efficient Contrastive Learning Approach for Mitigating Background Bias: Proposed CLAD, a novel and
  efficient contrastive learning approach that achieved State-of-the-Art on the Background challenge
  dataset. Work published at BMVC.
- **Uniform Robustness Evaluation of bio-inspired models:** Developed a novel testbed to evaluate the performance of biologically inspired vision models, specifically to account for the robustness against

out-of-distribution samples. This work helped set the standard in the field to align model quality between researchers. The evaluation pipeline is available on GitHub and was presented at **CVPR** NeuroVision 2022.

- Generation of adversarial foggy images for Robustness Evaluation: Pioneered GAN-based creation of
  adversarial foggy images, marking the forefront of adversarial weather attack exploration within this
  domain. Work published at WACV.
- Metric design for Robustness Evaluation under varying Weather Conditions: Pioneered a new metric to
  gauge the robustness of object detection networks within navigation systems across diverse weather
  conditions. Oral presentation at ICIP.
- Enhancing Neural Network Robustness via Latent Perturbations: Proposed a novel adversarial training
  method based on perturbations in the latent space to increase the robustness of neural networks. Work
  published at IJCAI.

### **Selected Publications**

- HM, M. Herzog, P. Frossard, "Eren: Enhancing deep learning robustness through image pre-processing," (Under Review), 2024.
- **HM**, M. Herzog, P. Frossard, "Frequency-based vulnerability analysis of deep learning models against image corruptions," (Under Review), 2023.
- **HM**, O. Choung, M. Herzog, P. Frossard, "Empirical advocacy of bio-inspired models for robust image recognition," **CVPR** NeuroVision Workshop, 2022.
- K. Wang, HM, O. Choung, M. Herzog, P. Frossard, "CLAD: A contrastive learning based approach for background debiasing," BMVC, 2022.
- **HM**, V. Balasubramanian, "A Little Fog for a Large Turn," **WACV**, 2020.
- N. Kumari, M. Singh, A. Sinha, HM, B. Krishnamurthy, V. Balasubramanian, "Harnessing the Vulnerability of Latent Layers in Adversarially Trained Models," IJCAI, 2019.
- **HM**, S. Channappayya, "An Evaluation Metric for Object Detection Algorithms in Autonomous Navigation Systems and its Application to a Real-time Alerting System," **ICIP**, 2018 (Oral).

\*Complete List on Google Scholar

#### **Skills**

**Programming** Python, C, C++, Java, Matlab

Frameworks
Pytorch, Tensorflow, Seaborn, Matplotlib, Sklearn, Git, Latex, Illustrator
Languages
English (Fluent), French (Basic), Korean (Int.), Hindi (Native), Telugu (Native)

## **Awards and Recognition**

- Qualified for **JICA Scholarship**, 2018.
- JENESYS Scholarship 2017.
- Special Recognition for a Young Team, IEEE SP CUP, 2016.
- Top 10 teams of IEEE SP CUP, 2016.
- Academic Excellence Award, IIT Hyderabad, 2014.
- Qualified for KVPY 2013.

#### **Personal Interests**

• Strength Training, Music, Cooking.

## **Community Service**

- Reviewer for ECML, CVPR, TIP, ICVGIP.
- TA for Signal Processing & Deep Learning courses.
- Supervision of many Masters students projects.